Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- May 1940 to October 1940. (Reel 15)
  - July, 1940, 3 (Reel 15)
    Mitchell began to press upon his fellow STFU leaders a plan to secure affiliation with the AF of L. In this connection, see his memorandum to David Dubinsky, President of the ILGWU, on organizing agricultural workers (June 24), and his memorandum to the AF of L (n.d. [July, 1940]), his letters to Butler and Blaine Treadway reporting on his negotiations with AF of L officials and the minutes of the NEC meeting which decided to go ahead with Mitchell's proposal (20). Other items of special interest include: minutes of a hearing held by WPA to investigate the STFU's complaint against WPA officials in Pemiscot County, Missouri (3), and an exchange between Mitchell and Butler on the conscription bill then before Congress (27, 28)
  - August, 1940, 4 (Reel 15)
    A dispute arose between Mitchell and Butler on the question of AF of L affiliation. Mitchell wished to create a new AF of L International, with which the STFU would, in turn, affiliate; Butler wanted direct affiliation. The merits of the two proposals were debated in the correspondence throughout the month until the NEC met in special session (31). The NEC also gave considerable attention to the problems at the Delta and Providence Cooperative Farms. Another issue of equal prominence in the August correspondence was the case of Robert L. Moore, a Missouri STFU organizer accused of accepting money from politicians, including those backing Senator Harry S. Truman, on the promise of swinging the union vote; see the minutes of Moore's trial before the Missouri County Central Council (Sept. 8). Finally, there are copies of statements before the House Committee on Interstate Migration by Mitchell, Brooks Hayes, John D. Rust, and Rupert B. Vance (14)
  - September, 1940, 5 (Reel 15)
    Discussion continued on the bid for AF of L affiliation; see especially the exchange between Mitchell and Butler (7, 17) and Butler's letters to the STFU locals (4, 12). The NEC sent a long letter to the Trustees of the Cooperative Farms, claiming that the recent investigation did not deal with the true grievances of union members on the farms (20)
  - October, 1940, 6 (Reel 15)
    The AF of L turned down the STFU proposal for affiliation; see the letter from AF of L President William Green, explaining the decision (23). In the wake of this development, the NEC met in special session on October 13; the full minutes reveal the confusion and desperation of the STFU leaders. A major topic toward the end of the month was the activities of O.H. Whitfield, the former STFU organizer who was reported to be stirring up racial hatred in Missouri and Texas for the benefit of a UCAPAWA organizing drive. On Whitfield, see especially J.E. Clayton's reports from Texas (18,31) and Butler's letters to W.M. Tanner and F.R. Betton on stopping Whitfield in Missouri (25, 29).
- November 1940 to December 1940, Undated 1940, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1940. (Reel 16)
  - November and December, 1940, 1 (Reel 16)
    There is an interesting exchange between Butler and Mitchell on Butler's proposal for bringing agricultural workers under the NLRB (Nov. 4,7). The only other issue of special interest is a campaign by the WDL to abolish the Virginia poll tax and to free Odell Waller, a black Virginia sharecropper sentenced to death for the murder of his landlord. The papers include various leaflets and WDL press releases on the Waller case (Nov. 9, 15; Dec. 18, 21), as well as a letter from WDL staff member Pauli Murray (Nov. 27). Pauli Murray also wrote about the case of Isaac Mosely, a black Missouri sharecropper serving a life sentence for killing his riding boss (Dec. 17)
  - No Date, 1940, 2 (Reel 16)
    Childhood Days, a 15-page typewritten account of his childhood and early career by H.L. Mitchell; a press release on the STFU memorandum to the FSA on the Poplar Bluff encampment; a memorandum to the Finance Committee of the ILGWU from J.R. Butler; legal papers relating to the Dyess Colony, including the articles of incorporation for both Dyess and the Missco Homestead Association; memorandum from J.L. Cummins to Brooks Hays on the mismanagement of Missco Homestead; STFU statement, probably to a Congressional committee, on increased appropriations for the NYA; letter of instructions to new organizers; "The Southern Tenant Farmers Union -- 1940", a booklet by J.R. Butler and Howard Kester; "Suggestions for Organizing Junior Locals of the STFU"; STFU Song Book
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1940, 3 (Reel 16)
    Folder 542 -- Complaints to the AAA. Folder 543 -- Materials written for the STFU Educational Program. Includes primarily instructional booklets written by Evelyn Smith. Folder 554 -- Testimony of various public figures before the House Committee on the Interstate Migration, Oklahoma City, Okla., Sept. 19 and 20, 1940. No STFU representatives appeared. Folder 557 -- Not Filmed. Folder 558 -- Returns from the 1940 Crop Survey. Folder 559 -- List of members in good standing as reported by the locals, Jan. 1, 1940. Folder 560 -- Monthly reports from local secretaries.
- Miscellaneous Union Business 1940 (continued) and January 1941 to March 1941. (Reel 17)
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1940 (continued), 1 (Reel 17)
    Folder 561 -- Reports from organizer J.F. Hynds in Arkansas. Folder 562 -- Reports from organizer W.M. Tanner in Missouri and Arkansas, and one report from D.A. Griffin in Arkansas. Folder 563 -- Reports of County Secretaries from Pemiscot County, Missouri, and Woodruff County, Arkansas. Folder 564 -- Not Filmed
  - January, 1941, 2 (Reel 17)
    The union's correspondence for January primarily concerns the Seventh Annual STFU Convention held at Little Rock on Jan. 31 to Feb. 2. The convention papers, all filed at Jan. 31, include: the Annual Financial Report for 1940, President's and Secretary's Report, Vice-President's report by F.R. Betton, "Put the Man of the Land Back on the Land: A New Policy and Program for the STFU" by H.L. Mitchell, and the Proceedings. The convention was supposed to meet in Memphis, but was shifted to Little Rock due to racial tensions, as Butler explained to F.R. Betton (1). Kester's relationship for the STFU became an important issue during the month; see Mitchell's report to Butler on his conversation with Kester (9) and Kester's three-page letter to Butler, setting forth his views on the union (28). Finally, a dispute arose between Butler and the NSW policy committee, with Butler claiming that the committee was trying to control the union's affairs (2,10,16)
  - February, 1941, 3 (Reel 17)
    A furor arose over a statement Mitchell made at the convention that "There is no basis for trade-unionism in Southern agriculture". Butler claimed that Mitchell was trying to turn a legitimate union into a crusade and threatened to resign if Mitchell did not retract his speech. On the dispute, the papers include a statement by Butler and a statement apparently written by Mitchell (9 -- note: it is not clear whether Mitchell's statement was read at the Feb. 9 or the Jan. 30 NEC meeting), the minutes of the NEC meeting which adjudicated the matter (9), and a press release which reported that Mitchell had repudiated his convention speech (10). The rift led Kester to submit his letter of resignation from the STFU (27); see also Butler's reply to Kester (March 13). The other major topic in the February correspondence is the matter of arrangements for NSW
  - March, 1941, 4 (Reel 17)
    National Sharecroppers Week was held on March 2 to 9; the papers include a good deal of correspondence about travel arrangements, etc. NSW was a great success, but the STFU leaders and the NSW Policy Committee in New York over whether the proceeds would be sent in 12 monthly installments, or as the union requested them (27 to 30). In addition to NSW, there is a series of letters from William L. Harris, County Agent of Hartford County, Conn., on the matter of providing temporary employment for approximately 500 STFU members in the Connecticut tobacco fields (5, 12, 21).
- April 1941 to July 1941. (Reel 18)
  - April, 1941, 1 (Reel 18)
    The dispute over NSW continued and resulted in the decision to form a permanent "National Sharecroppers Committee", independent of the WDL, to raise money for the STFU and other sharecropper causes. The key documents include: a report from Betton and Mitchell on their negotiations with the NSW Policy Committee (11), minutes of the NEC meeting which took up the question (19), and an exchange of correspondence between Mitchell and Harold L. Oram on setting up the new committee (22, 25, 29). The union also began a campaign to amend the Agricultural Adjustment Act to ensure a minimum wage for farm labor; see the STFU memorandum on this subject (16) and Mitchell's correspondence with AF of L officials asking for their support (28). Finally, a letter from Mitchell to Kester provides considerable information on the status of the union's organizing drive (27)
  - May, 1941, 2 (Reel 18)
    The effort to obtain a minimum wage for farm workers went into high gear. See the STFU press release on the campaign, including a copy of the bill as introduced by Senator William Langer of North Dakota and a three-page statement by Mitchell (2). There is a four-page letter from Butler to Secretary of Agriculture Claude R. Wickard, trying to convince him to incorporate the measure into his own legislative program (16), as well as correspondence on the bill from Congressman Jerry Voorhis of California (April 30, 19, 27), Frank McCallister (20), and Benjamin Marsh, Executive Secretary of The People's Lobby (April 30, 2, 6, 8)
  - June, 1941, 3 (Reel 18)
    The Farm Security Administration, under attack from the Farm Bureau, became highly receptive to the idea of cooperating with the STFU on organizing drives in northern Alabama and other areas. Mitchell moved quickly to exploit the opportunity; see his letters to FSA officials (16) and his detailed explanation of the situation to Norman Thomas (25). For further information on the organizing drive, see Mitchell's repots to Butler on his trip to Alabama, Texas, and Oklahoma (18,22) and Butler's summary report to the NEC (26). Correspondence continued between Mitchell and Harold L. Oram on the matter of selecting a chairman for the projected National Sharecroppers Committee. Sam Franklin wrote from the DCF to express his pique at the STFU's recent investigation of the co-op farms (25), and J.E. Clayton wrote on the campaign of his friend Lyndon B. Johnson for the U.S. Senate (30).
  - July, 1941, 4 (Reel 18)
    The NEC met on July 11 and 12; the papers include the agenda, minutes, proposed budget, and a report by Mitchell on "Cooperation with the FSA" (11). In addition, there are reports to the NEC on the STFU organizing drive from Odis Sweeden in Oklahoma (3), Noah P. Graham in Missouri (8), W.M. Tanner in Missouri (9), John Alford in Arkansas (11), and from J.E. Clayton in Texas and Missouri (12). Plans for cooperation with the FSA continued to develop; see FSA Administrator C. B. Baldwin to his Regional Directors on the subject (2), as well as Mitchell's letters to Alabama FSA officials (18) and to Clayton and Betton (31). Other items of special interest include: correspondence with J.D. Overholt, who decided to donate $5,000 to the union (6,19,31); a speech by Hugh L. Gray, President of the planters-oriented Delta Council, replying to a recent radio address by Mitchell (18), and Butler to Walter White of the NAACP, asking him to join the union in its attempt to save Edmondson, Ark., an all-black town threatened with destruction by the surrounding white planters (18). For further information on the Edmondson case, see the correspondence of lawyer K.T. Sutton throughout 1941.
- August 1941 to December 1941. (Reel 19)
  - August, 1941, 1 (Reel 19)
    In August and September, organizers F. R. Betton and J.E. Clayton began sending carbon copies of all their correspondence to headquarters. Taken together, the materials they sent provide a detailed picture of STFU efforts to aid and organize the black community. There is much correspondence on the organizing drive in northern Alabama; see especially Mitchell's memoranda on Alabama organizing (4,19) and reports from organizer W.M. Tanner. Mitchell also spoke with FSA and AAA officials in Little Rock about similar cooperation in Arkansas and reported on his conversations to Butler (20) and Betton (21). Finally, there is a survey of food prices paid by STFU members, compiled by the Office of Price Administration (8)
  - September, 1941, 2 (Reel 19)
    Mitchell wrote Dr. George S. Mitchell at the FSA that the National Farmers Union and the STFU had worked out an organizing agreement (2), but James G. Patton, President of the Farmers Union, heatedly denied the STFU claim (9). Clayton and Betton pursued their long-standing dream of purchasing the Lowdon plantation near Gould, Ark. for the purpose of resettling black tenant farmers after J.D. Overholt offered them $5,000 for the project, but the plans fell through (10, 11, 16, 17, 23). Clayton reported on his organizing trip to Louisiana (23). Lastly, a letter arrived from C.P. Dye, describing his work among Arkansas sharecroppers in 1932 and 1933, before the STFU was founded (4)
  - October, 1941, 3 (Reel 19)
    Notable topics in the correspondence include the organizing drive in Alabama and hearings by a Senate Subcommittee headed by Claude Pepper of Florida on the Langer minimum wage bill for farm workers. The NEC met on Oct. 9 and 10; the agenda, minutes, and proposed budget appear, as well as a complete list of STFU locals, with information on the number of paid-up members in each local (9). On the Edmondson, Arkansas case described above, there is a memorandum to the WDL (13) and letters from Frank McCallister (13) and K.T. Sutton (14) describing their work on the case. A copy of the court brief prepared by Sutton accompanies his letter. Finally, there are reports from Mitchell (20) and Clayton (Nov. 1) on their conversations with Will Alexander, who offered to help raise funds for the union
  - November, 1941, 4 (Reel 19)
    The new Alabama District Council sent forth a series of resolutions, all aimed at changing the STFU Constitution (8,20,29, Dec. 3). In a long and detailed letter to James G. Patton, President of the National Farmer's Union (NFU), Mitchell explained the problems of organizing farm labor in the South and proposed that the STFU become the "Southern Division" of the NFU (Oct. 30); correspondence between Mitchell and Patton continued throughout November with no result (7,14,17,25). Other interesting items include: a three-page letter from Kester on his campaign to liberalize the South through its rural churches (7), a report from Frank McCallister on the UCAPAWA delegation to the CIO Annual Convention (22), and Mitchell to Jonathan Daniels, describing the union's activities in Alabama (24)
  - December, 1941, 5 (Reel 19)
    Convention preparations dominate the correspondence for December. There is an analysis of the union's membership drive (31), as well as more detailed information on STFU locals in Mississippi contained in Butler's letters to organizer E.O. Cistrunk (9,16). On Oklahoma, see Sweeden's ability to organize the state (27) and Sweeden's embittered reply (29). Sam Franklin wrote at length on racial friction at the Providence Co-op Farm (19), and Mitchell gave Jonathan Daniels his assessment of how the war would affect the STFU (26).
- Undated and Miscellaneous Union Business 1941 and January 1942 to February 1942. (Reel 20)
  - No Date, 1941, 1 (Reel 20)
    Survey of wages and food prices in Missouri, 1940-1941; Agreement between Local 56 of the AMCBWNA and the P.J. Ritter Co. of Bridgeton, N.J.; proposal for a Missouri Agricultural Workers Council, most likely written by O.H. Whitfield; letter to Secretary of Agricultural Claude R. Wickard, suggesting that he appoint James P. Davis of the AAA office at Little Rock as his "Negro assistant"; flyers for STFU mass meetings; notes for a speech by Mitchell at the Hod Carriers' Union Annual Convention in St. Louis, Mo
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1941, 2 (Reel 20)
    Folders 658 and 659 -- Not Filmed. Folder 660 -- Monthly reports of locals. Folder 661 -- Charter Applications. Folders 662 to 675 -- Organizers' weekly reports
  - January, 1942, 3 (Reel 20)
    Papers for the Eighth Annual STFU Convention, held at Sheffield, Alabama on Jan. 7 to 10, are far more extensive than the papers for previous conventions. They include the program, list of delegates, reports from Butler, Betton, Mitchell, and J.F. Hynds (on his work settling claims against the AAA), the "STFU Sign Manual and Ritual", approximately fifty resolutions passed at the convention, including one on the retirement of J.R. Butler as STFU President, and a thoroughly revised union Constitution. A set of typed minutes, with handwritten corrections, does appear, but the printed Proceedings does not. For the first time since the mid-1930s, the STFU encountered large-scale violence when a group of planters broke up two union meetings at Caruthersville, Mo. on Jan. 16 and 23, and the correspondence from Jan. 17 onward is almost solely devoted to the incident. Major figures involved in the Caruthersville affair include Mitchell, Missouri organizer W.M. Tanner, Governor Forrest C. Donnell of Missouri, Frank McCallister, Secretary of the Southern WDL, and William Green, President of the AF of L
  - February, 1942, 4 (Reel 20)
    The investigation into the violence at Caruthersville, Mo. continued throughout February and might best be followed through the letters of Frank McCallister, Secretary of the Southern WDL. In this connection, see also Mitchell to McCallister, providing good background information on the incident (3) and an exchange between STFU lawyer Claude Cooper and Gov. Donnell of Missouri (12, 27). There is a statement from Mitchell to the Joint Legislative Economy Committee (U.S. Congress) arguing against the abolishment of FSA (13) and a long letter from Mitchell to NAACP Secretary Walter White on the case of Edmondson, Ark. (18).
- March 1942 to September 1942. (Reel 21)
  - March, 1942, 1 (Reel 21)
    National Sharecroppers Week was held March 1 to 8; the papers include the NSW pamphlet, a list of sponsors, and an "Outline for Speakers" (1). Negotiations continued with James Patton concerning possible STFU affiliation with the National Farmers' Union (7,13,23,25) and the papers include a nine-page transcript of the debate on this question at the March 21 meeting of the NEC (21). Also under discussion during March was a plan to start an STFU Cooperative Marketing and Purchasing Association in Alabama; see especially Mitchell to Roy E. Raley, reporting on his conversations with Alabama FSA officials on securing their help for the venture (26). Mitchell to Arthur G. McDowell provides particularly good background information on the Caruthersville incident in January (14)
  - April, 1942, 2 (Reel 21)
    At the request of Will Alexander, Mitchell undertook a study of the operations of the Farm Bureau Federation in the South. The papers include his letters to Alexander (1,17)) and a lengthy report with attached statements from 98 small farmers claiming they were forced to join the Farm Bureau in order to continue receiving their government subsidy payments (17). The Southern Conference for Human Welfare met at Nashville on April 19 to 21; some correspondence relating to the Conference appears, but the program and Proceedings do not. There is a press release on the STFU marketing cooperative in Alabama (n.d. [April]), and a letter from Clayton to Congressman Lyndon B. Johnson, asking him to help arrange a $90,000 loan for a group of black farmers near Austin, Texas who wish to purchase a plantation (21)
  - May, 1942, 3 (Reel 21)
    Mitchell's attempt to gain wide publicity for his Farm Bureau report ran into a snag when the Associated Press, featuring a possible suit for libel, refused to cover the story. See the STFU's press releases on the report (4) and letters from Frank McCallister (5,8) and Benjamin Marsh (16) on their efforts to get proper coverage. There are also two interesting letters reacting to the report from AF of L president William Green (4) and Aubrey Williams (5) The Articles of Incorporation of the Arkansas Farmers Co- Operative Association appear during this month (12), as does Mitchell's statement before the House Committee Investigating National Defense Migration (8)
  - June, 1942, 4 (Reel 21)
    There are two interesting letters on the situation in Missouri, one from Arthur G. McDowell to Frank McCallister reporting on UCAPAWA activities there (2) and one from Mitchell to McDowell on the current status and the STFU in Missouri (16). An apparently complete list of STFU locals, with an estimate of the number of active members in each, appears immediately after the GEC minutes (27; note: the NEC changes its name to the "General Executive Council" as of this date). Finally, there is a letter from the Secretary of Agriculture responding to Mitchell's Farm Bureau report (30)
  - July and August, 1942, 5 (Reel 21)
    The only notable event of the summer was the creation of the STFU Legal Department with Arkansas lawyer K.T. Sutton in charge to handle the various legal problems of union members. The reader may follow the progress of the new department through the correspondence of Sutton and in the case reports he sent to headquarters (n.d. [July], Aug. 6, n.d. [August]). Other major topics during the summer include the union's desperate search for financial support and the new co-operative associations in Arkansas and Alabama. On the latter subject, see especially Mitchell's letter to Betton and Raley (15)
  - September, 1942, 6 (Reel 21)
    The union held a Wage Conference in Memphis on Sept. 7 to demand the same wages for cotton picking which the government had guaranteed to Mexican workers imported by the War Manpower Commission. Papers related to the conference include a press release (2), circulars, petitions, and handbills distributed at the conference (7), and the draft of a press release which provides a rough account of what took place (9). Toward the end of the month Mitchell went to Washington to try to convince the Manpower Commission to send STFU members to Arizona in place of Mexicans; see his report from Washington (25), the memorandum he submitted to the Commission (28), and his letter to the US Employment Service in Arizona offering to send 1,000 workers (26).
- October 1942 to December 1942, and Undated 1942. (Reel 22)
  - October, 1942, 1 (Reel 22)
    The WMC took up Mitchell's offer and the planning began in earnest. FSA Administrator C.B. Baldwin supplied detailed information on prevailing conditions about wage rates in California, but claimed to know little about Arizona and New Mexico (13). Odis Sweeden, a former STFU leader in Oklahoma, happened to be in Arizona and sent Mitchell the missing information (15); the sheet of paper on which Sweeden answered Mitchell's questions is lost, but see Mitchell's transcription of Sweeden's replies (20). There are three comprehensive memoranda in which Mitchell set forth his position: one to the War Manpower Advisory Committee, written in response to a request from Walter Reuther (6), one to the WMC itself (15), and one to the Farmers' Union over possible affiliation came to a somewhat caustic end; see the letter from NFU President James Patton (5) and Mitchell's memorandum describing the full history of the negotiations (9)
  - November, 1942, 2 (Reel 22)